<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-05T07:37:17+01:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Half Past Yellow | Blog</title><subtitle>Game Development and other HPY Happenings</subtitle><author><name>Half Past Yellow</name></author><entry><title type="html">Introducing Fai</title><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2025/02/05/Introducing-Fai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Fai" /><published>2025-02-05T16:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-05T16:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2025/02/05/Introducing-Fai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2025/02/05/Introducing-Fai.html"><![CDATA[<p>We had a few questions come up on our Discord about the main character of <i>Tempest Tower</i> and their role in the world of Trip Space. It’s time to properly meet Fai.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/BlogJump.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div>

<h2 class="section-heading">The world of Trip Space</h2>
<p>The concept of Trip Space was originally created as a backdrop for our First-Person Puzzle game, <i>Spectacle</i>. It is a surreal, abstract collection of floating islands and strange vistas that living creatures visit while dreaming, or meditating, or... by other means. Visitors to Trip Space manifest as Peepers (cute little eyeball creatures with wings), they are able to observe this strange world, but they rely on the native Trip Tenders to properly shepherd them through their experience.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/BlogPeep.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div>

<p>Living and visiting Trip Space was always tranquil, but the recent invasion of Creepers has turned the experience into a nightmare! An ominous dark fog has engulfed the many islands of Trip Space and it feels impossible to stand against the horde that emerges from it. This is where <i>Tempest Tower</i> takes place.</p>

<h2 class="section-heading">Who is Fai</h2>
<p>Fai is a Trip Tender, a native inhabitant of Trip Space and a caretaker of the world. Fai is a bit of an underachiever and definitely didn’t volunteer for the role of hero, they are underprepared and easily distracted, but they are also the only Trip Tender around.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/ToBeABat.png" alt="Early concept of the Tutorial Bat">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Fai is a curious soul, but the Batsplainer is having none of it</span>

<p>With the player’s help, Fai will become a battle-hardened veteran, and an expert strategist. They will learn to build crazy contraptions as well as use the world of Trip Space against the invasive Creeper forces, and most importantly, they will save the many Peepers who still visit Trip Space.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/ActionGif.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div>

<p><b>Fun Fact:</b> We used the name Fai, because it is pronounced similarly to the Danish word Fej, which means coward (and is also close to the word for sweep).</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/FaiName.PNG" alt="screenshot of google translate">
</div>

<h2 class="section-heading">Early Concepts</h2>
<p>The native inhabitants of Trip Space being lizard people was an idea that we carried over from <i>Spectacle</i>. We wanted to use the backdrop of Trip Space to embrace the world of conspiracy theories, so the native inhabitants had to be a cult-like group of lizards.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/SpectacleConcept.png" alt="Spectacle Concepts">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Early concepts of Trip Tenders</span>

<p>One of the first mechanics we discussed for <i>Tempest Tower</i> was the ability for our main character to Gust/Push/Waft at objects and enemies in the game. This led to very early concepts of a janitor/caretaker character that used a broom to clean objects and create gusts. We loved the idea of a caretaker character who is forced to go above and beyond to protect their world.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/Cleaning.PNG" alt="sweeping concepts">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">The earliest version of the game had players sweeping up goo for resources.</span>

<p>The idea of the broom becoming a multipurpose tool for building, painting, and digging came a bit later. The broom became such a key part of Fai’s silhouette that it didn’t make sense to see them use any other tools. Thankfully, the game is generally a bit goofy, so it doesn’t feel that strange to see a character digging up a plant with a floppy broom. </p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/Building.png" alt="building concepts">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Swiss army broom!</span>

<p>Now, drawing a concept and designing a character is one thing but of course we had to translate it to 3D, which is often a lot easier said than done!</p>

<h2 class="section-heading">From 2D to 3D</h2>
<p>We were lucky enough to already have a base model to work from. Even though <i>Spectacle</i> was a First-Person game, we did have an “out of body” mechanic that meant we had to model our main character so they could be seen from any angle. This meant we had a place to start, but Fai was very much their own lizard so there was still a lot to do. The yellow rubber gloves really pop alongside Fai’s purple cloak and the trashcan backpack was just for added bounce and style.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/TheThirdDimention.png" alt="3D turnaround">
</div>

<p>The bouncy animation style is a mix of talented animation work from the HPY team and the Boing Kit plugin for Unity. We gained a lot of experience with expressive movement while working on our previous game, <i>Time on Frog Island</i>, and that did not go to waste here.</p>
<p>To get the perfect look for Fai in game, we are using ramped lighting with a custom ramp texture. We are using an emissive texture to get Fai’s eyes to glow and applying a matcap texture to enhance the soft lighting. An occlusion map is used, mainly to remove indirect lighting from Fai’s face so that the hood/cap can look like they are having a bigger impact on the lighting.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/BlogSpin.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div>

<h2 class="section-heading">Get Involved!</h2>
<p>If <i>Tempest Tower</i> sounds like a game that you would like to play, remember to Wishlist it on <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/3123800/Tempest_Tower/">Steam!</a> Other than that, the best way to stay informed about <i>Tempest Tower</i> is to join our <a href="https://hpy.lol/Discord">Discord</a> and/or check out our Social Media channels (<a href="https://hpy.lol/BlueSky">Blue Sky</a>, <a href="https://hpy.lol/Twitter">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/HalfPastYellow">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://hpy.lol/Instagram">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://hpy.lol/TikTok">TikTok</a>).</p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/3123800/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>

<p>We will have a public Demo releasing very soon, so you will be able to try out the Tutorial plus a special expanded level that we built to show off the intended difficulty of the full game. If soon is too far away and you happen to live in Copenhagen, you can play the <i>Tempest Tower</i> Demo next week at <a href="https://www.awesomegames.show/showcase2025">Tomorrow’s Awesome Game Showcase!</a> We hope to see you there.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<a href="https://www.awesomegames.show/showcase2025" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/19/TempestTAGS.png" alt="TAGS image"></a>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Max</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We had a few questions come up on our Discord about the main character of Tempest Tower and their role in the world of Trip Space. It’s time to properly meet Fai.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tempest Tower - Announcement Trailer!</title><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2025/01/11/Tempest-Tower-First-Look.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tempest Tower - Announcement Trailer!" /><published>2025-01-11T16:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-11T16:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2025/01/11/Tempest-Tower-First-Look</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2025/01/11/Tempest-Tower-First-Look.html"><![CDATA[<p>Happy New Year from the whole team at Half Past Yellow! We hope you had a good holiday break and that you’re ready for all the great games coming out in 2025 🎉</p>
<p>Speaking of great games coming out in 2025, check out the First Look Trailer for <i>Tempest Tower</i>! Coming soon to early access.</p>

<div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 rounded">
	<iframe class="embed-responsive-item" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ik1uElp59Y0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>

<p><i>Tempest Tower</i> redefines Tower Defense with a dynamic blend of classic base-building and electrifying player-driven combat. Explore, plan, and meticulously construct your base during the Build Phase. Execute, adapt, and ruthlessly brawl with hordes of Creepers during the Action Phase. Every level is a thrilling test of strategy and skill!</p>
<p>If that sounds like your kind of game, then consider giving <i>Tempest Tower</i> a wishlist on Steam so you don’t miss out when the game releases in the near future 👀</p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/3123800/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>

<h2 class="section-heading">Get Involved!</h2>
<p>We will continue to post news and dev-blogs here whenever we have anything big to share and we will be making better use of the Steam Community Hub when we get closer to launch. Until then, the best way to stay informed about all things <i>Tempest Tower</i> is to join us on Discord! We have a few big things coming in the next 2 months and we can’t wait to hear what you think.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<a href="https://hpy.lol/discord" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/17/DiscordImg.png" alt="Discord Image"></a>
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Join us on Discord!</span> 

<h2 class="section-heading">Making the Trailer</h2>
<p>For all those who are interested, I thought I would pull back the curtain a bit on how the trailer was made.</p>
<p>The first look trailer for <i>Tempest Tower</i> was made by James Mcgregor (corfiz.com). We worked with James on most of the <i>Time on Frog Island</i> trailers and really enjoyed the process, so we were ecstatic to find out that he was available to help on <i>Tempest Tower</i> as well.</p>
<p>Having worked with James before, it was pretty easy to get started. I made a trailer brief that outlined the deadline, expected length, links to music from the game, what to show, and what to avoid showing. The brief also included some reference trailers that I thought captured the expected vibe and pace. After that, I created a Trailer Branch that James could work from so that he could easily set up shots and create sets inside the Unity project.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/18/branches.PNG" alt="showcase of git branches">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Having a trailer branch allowed us to quickly update his working version with bug fixes and new art.</span>

<p>Once James had access to the game, he could spend some time playing and generating ideas before the two of us sat down for a proper meeting about how to best show off the game. James could then get to work on a quick blockout (descriptive text explaining each shot to show the overall timings of the trailer) for the time to give any first notes on.</p>
<p>Most of our notes and discussions were done through Discord or using frame.io, which we could use to give specific feedback on the current version of the trailer. The earliest iteration of the trailer took a bit too long to get to the action, but other than that, the skeleton of the initial blockout held strong through the whole process.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/18/frameIO.PNG" alt="screenshot from Frame IO">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Notes could be made directly on the timeline, it is also possible to draw on the frame with arrows and circles.</span>

<p>After seeing the first proper cut of the trailer, it was quite clear to the team that our current music selection didn’t really have anything that matched the trailer’s energy. The trailer needed to be fast moving (and the game can be hectic too), but nothing we had on hand really fit.</p>
<p>We are lucky enough to have both a full-time composer and a full-time sound designer at Half Past Yellow, so Nino (our composer) made the decision to make something bespoke. It took around 4 days for him to put together a track that properly fit the trailer pace and the experiments have bled back into game music.</p>
<p>Nino's thoughts at that time "<i>Seeing the draft of the trailer made me question the whole musical direction of the game. So, the only reasonable thing to do was to let go the current direction and just vibe with what I have on the screen in front of me. Shortly after, it clicked, and everything started making sense again. The music direction and overall experience of the game had been changed for me. Since then, I have been revisiting the previous tracks I made for the game, sometimes re-doing them from scratch. Whatever it takes for the best experience.</i>"</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/18/Nino_Pic.jpg" alt="Picture of Nino the composer">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Nino during a post music video photoshoot.</span>

<p>Once we had a final trailer edit and music track, it was time to add SFX and balance the audio. Goran (our sound designer) previously worked in film and TV, which is a godsend in situations like this. For the purposes of highlighting specific sounds and properly balancing the SFX and music, it was easier for him to dub over the trailer than worry about using the existing sounds in the clips that James recorded.</p>
<p>I asked Goran to write up some of his thoughts: "<i>The video was action-packed, so finding the right balance between composition and sound design was crucial. The trailer began with a gameplay-driven scene to give a brief glimpse of the world, followed by a gradual buildup into a high-energy trailer sequence. This transition emphasized the core gameplay mechanics while maintaining a strong focus on the sound effects that complemented the music. Since the music was percussive, the percussive elements of the sound design naturally blended in, almost as if they were part of the music itself.</i>"</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/18/Goran_Pic.jpg" alt="Picture of Goran the composer">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Goran inside his home studio.</span>

<p>Balancing the audio is always a friendly fight between Nino and Goran. They both live in the same city, so they met up in person to produce the final audio mix and celebrate the completed trailer.</p>
<p>Eventually, the trailer was complete. We handed off the final audio mix to James along with the art for the end slate and layout mock-ups. From start to finish, I took just under 3 weeks to put everything together and we couldn’t be happier with the results. I hope that you enjoy this first look at <i>Tempest Tower</i> and that you will keep an eye out for more news about the game and its production!</p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/3123800/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>

<div class="text-center">
<a href="https://hpy.lol/discord" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/17/DiscordImg.png" alt="Discord Image"></a>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Max</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Happy New Year from the whole team at Half Past Yellow! We hope you had a good holiday break and that you’re ready for all the great games coming out in 2025 🎉 Speaking of great games coming out in 2025, check out the First Look Trailer for Tempest Tower! Coming soon to early access.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tempest Tower is coming to Early Access</title><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/12/18/Early-Access-Announcement.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tempest Tower is coming to Early Access" /><published>2024-12-18T16:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-18T16:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/12/18/Early-Access-Announcement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/12/18/Early-Access-Announcement.html"><![CDATA[<p>We have a much shorter “game news” style blog post this time, mainly aimed at catching everyone up on our plans with <i>Tempest Tower</i>.</p>
<p>We are excited to announce that <i>Tempest Tower</i> will be our first self-published game. We plan to launch the game into Steam Early Access during the first half of 2025 and work closely with our community to build a game we are all proud of.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet tw-align-center"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Time for <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PitchYaGame?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#PitchYaGame</a>!<br><br>Tempest Tower is an action-packed Tower Defence game with Platforming elements.<br><br>Protect your tower from hordes of enemies using crazy contraptions, powerful upgrades, or by simply jumping on their heads.<br><br>Find out more via Steam: <a href="https://t.co/TgRWSv1lUZ">https://t.co/TgRWSv1lUZ</a> <a href="https://t.co/1Z5s1j6TZR">pic.twitter.com/1Z5s1j6TZR</a></p>&mdash; 🟡 Half Past Yellow (@halfpastyellow) <a href="https://twitter.com/halfpastyellow/status/1852376038463979864?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 1, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> 

<h2 class="section-heading">Why Early Access?</h2>
<p>For <i>Tempest Tower</i>, we plan to fully embrace the open development style. We want to develop a strong community around the game, and we feel that the best way to do this is by getting players involved early and allowing them to shape the project with us.</p>
<p>We don’t yet know what the future holds, but we expect <i>Tempest Tower</i> to remain in Early Access for around 9 months. We will use that time to add content, quality of life features, and new game modes. The game will launch on Early Access as a tight experience with all core mechanics present, we aim to have 2-3 hours of base gameplay with endless extra hours of experimenting with loadouts and highscore hunting on top.</p>
<p>If you are interested in getting involved right now, I suggest joining our <a href="https://hpy.lol/discord">Discord server</a>. It has been fairly quiet over the last 18 months, but that will be changing as we move into next year!</p>
<div class="text-center">
<a href="https://hpy.lol/discord" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/17/DiscordImg.png" alt="Discord Image"></a>
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Join us on Discord!</span> 

<h2 class="section-heading">New Art, Who Dis?</h2>
<p>We are making this announcement alongside a big face lift to our Steam page. We have updated our capsule art, logo, and screenshots as well as finalised our store text so it can be translated in the new year. We have worked alongside another game development studio called <a href="https://bitegginc.com/">BitEgg</a> to update our Capsule Art and we couldn't be happier with the results, they have perfectly captured the vibe of <i>Tempest Tower</i> and we think that the new art really stands out in the Steam store.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/17/VerticalCap.jpg" alt="steam vertical capsule art">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Sometimes it's hard to pick favorites... But we can't get over how great the Vertical Capsule is!</span>

<h2 class="section-heading">More news coming soon!</h2>
<p>We will be properly showing <i>Tempest Tower</i> in motion for the first time when we reveal our first look trailer in early January. This will be our first big marketing push for the game and it will coincide with more news about what to expect from us in the run up to the games launch. Until then, we hope you have a relaxing holiday and a good new year!</p>
<p>That is all for now. If you want to learn more about <i>Tempest Tower</i>, you can check out the <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/3123800/">Steam Page</a> or our <a href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/08/19/Introducing-Tempest-Tower.html">previous</a> <a href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/10/30/Level-Design-in-Tempest-Tower.html">two</a> blog posts, and if you like the look of the game consider giving it a wishlist and following along with the community updates.</p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/3123800/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>]]></content><author><name>Max</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We have a much shorter “game news” style blog post this time, mainly aimed at catching everyone up on our plans with Tempest Tower. We are excited to announce that Tempest Tower will be our first self-published game. We plan to launch the game into Steam Early Access during the first half of 2025 and work closely with our community to build a game we are all proud of.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Level Design in Tempest Tower</title><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/10/30/Level-Design-in-Tempest-Tower.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Level Design in Tempest Tower" /><published>2024-10-30T16:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-30T16:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/10/30/Level-Design-in-Tempest-Tower</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/10/30/Level-Design-in-Tempest-Tower.html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post was originally going to be about how we create an understandable player story within the whimsical/abstract world of <i>Tempest Tower</i>. Then I started to see the #blocktober tag around Twitter and decided to write a different post instead. Specifically, about some early experimentation we did on <i>Tempest Tower</i> and how changes to the game design impacted the level design.</p>
<p>I don’t think that the hashtag has ever been as popular as <a href="https://www.polygon.com/2017/10/3/16408922/game-development-level-design">2017 when it was first started</a>, but us indie developers must use every algorithm bump we can.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Is <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/blocktober?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#blocktober</a> still a thing? We wanted to share some footage of a movement test on our new Tempest Tower level.<br>More info coming later in this months blog! <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ScreenshotSaturday?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#ScreenshotSaturday</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/indiedev?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#indiedev</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/gamedev?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#gamedev</a> <a href="https://t.co/f8gyCksYTn">pic.twitter.com/f8gyCksYTn</a></p>&mdash; 🟡 Half Past Yellow (@halfpastyellow) <a href="https://twitter.com/halfpastyellow/status/1845011845339381761?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">October 12, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> 

<h2 class="section-heading">What is a Level in <i>Tempest Tower</i>?</h2>
<p>Let’s start by quickly outlining what a level in <i>Tempest Tower</i> actually is. Each level is a standalone floating island; the terrain, enemy spawn points, and level segments are all handcrafted by a level designer, but there are some light procedural elements that change after every attempt.</p>
<p>At the start of a level, only a small portion of it is available to explore and build on. The rest of the level is covered in a thick fog. After successfully defending a wave, a section of the fog is pushed back, and a new segment of the level is revealed. Once the last section of the fog has been ousted, the player must defend one last wave in order to complete the level and return to the menu victorious.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/15/foglvl.png" alt="Fog Concept">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">An early concept of how levels are revealed incrementally</span>
<p>If the player is overwhelmed by a wave and loses their Main Tower, then they must start the level again. <i>Tempest Tower</i> rewards players who experiment with their loadout and try out different upgrades as they learn the layout of a level and how to deal with different enemies. You never know how things are going to interact.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/MapExpand.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">WIP map view showing how a level expands.</span> 

<h2 class="section-heading">Learning from <i>Time on Frog Island</i></h2>
<p>An important aspect of the <i>Tempest Tower</i> project is our ability to move quickly with ideas. Because of this, the decision was made early on to use a similar camera angle and movement style to our previous game, <i>Time on Frog Island</i>. Making this decision early allowed us to come into the project with some basic level design rules and a good understanding of how traversal should feel.</p>
<p><i>Time on Frog Island</i> sees the player doing a lot of running around so it was important to us that the act of traversing the island was as fun as possible (even when lost and slightly frustrated).</p>
<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/ToFIExplore.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">A quick loop around Frog Island at 250% speed!</span> 
<p>
<b>Key level design tenets from <i>ToFI</i>:</b>
<ul>
  <li> The island gains height/verticality the further ‘north’ that the player travels 
  <li> All designed/expected jumps in the game are possible with about 1 meter of leeway (the game is not built to be a hardcore platformer)
  <li> It is always clear when the player needs to jump (exposed rock visuals) 
  <li> The camera angle makes height differences in the geometry are difficult to parse so take off points for ‘1-way jumps’ should be marked clearly
  <li> If the player is ever completely obscured by terrain (which was used sparingly), the ground should be completely smooth and require no jumps to pass through  
</ul>
</p>
<p>If you have never played <i>Time on Frog Island</i> and I have managed to pique your interest with this blog, then I suggest you check out the <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1755950/Time_on_Frog_Island__Prologue/">Free Prologue Adventure</a> and see if it is a game for you!</p>

<h2 class="section-heading">Blockouting a level for <i>Tempest Tower</i></h2>
<p>While we are lucky to be starting with so much knowledge from <i>Time on Frog Island</i>, it was still necessary to find the fun within <i>Tempest Tower</i>. The rules above gave us a good place to start, but we had to be fast at creating new levels so we could properly test different gameplay features. Blockouting a level always went through three stages of focus; player movement, enemy paths, gameplay objects/items.</p>
<p>The base terrain is built up by connecting and overlapping pre-built platform pieces in order to create flat open areas, terraced hillsides, and connecting slopes. Pre-built rock shapes are used to plug holes, block jumps, and add visual variety to the space. We are using a world space triplanar shader for both the ground material as well as the exposed rock material so that we can guarantee that the terrain textures always line up. This does generate quite a bit of overlapping geometry, which we might need to revisit at a later date, but it isn’t currently a performance problem.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/LevelPieces.png" alt="Level Pieces">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Some of the many standardised level pieces we have for making levels.</span>
<p>Enemies cannot jump or drop off ledges, so platforming areas act as shortcuts between different sections of the level. We always build levels with a player movement focus first as it has the largest impact on the fun factor of a level. Levels can often feel a little bare at this point (see: the embedded tweet at the top of this post), but understanding how the player moves around a level is important to understand before moving onto the next step.</p>
<p>Once we have a good first pass on the overall level, the focus shifts to building enemy paths. A level in <i>Tempest Tower</i> needs to feel amazing (and ideally different) to traverse while empty as well as when it is filled with enemies. The route(s) that enemies take through the level can greatly affect the flow of the space, tight corridors become impassable while high cliffs can be more easily reached. Because of this, we are still making big changes to the base terrain while we decide how to weave enemy paths through it.</p>
<p>The final piece of the blockouting puzzle is the setup of game objects and items. These are gameplay relevant elements that the player can interact with and use during the level, (things like resource spawners, bombs, destructible blockers, etc.). Once added, the level is properly playable, and the designer can start to evaluate, refine and balance (which is where the real fun begins).</p>
<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/LevelBlockout.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">Level blockout timelapse.</span> 

<h2 class="section-heading">Early experimentation</h2>
<p>An action-packed Tower Defence with Platforming elements. This was the key one-liner that drove our early experimentation. We wanted to reward movement efficiency, smart planning, and the ability to react quickly when things go wrong.</p>
<p>The first iteration of <i>Tempest Tower</i> focused too much on movement. After setting up some defences and starting the wave, the player was expected to effectively ignore enemies in their mad dash for resource collection. This allowed us to create levels that were more vertical and maze like, but it felt counter intuitive to testers (they wanted to engage more with the enemies).</p>
<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/EarlyLevelBlockout2.png" alt="Early Blockout">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Our first full level blockout for pitching at GDC.</span>
<p>In this early stage of development, the player collected the gold/ore/currency for building new defences by clearing away gunk from specific spawner locations. Because of this, the design of early levels used a lot more verticality, included more jumps, and had more gaps in the terrain. The game design also placed the most emphasis on route planning and execution so levels had more of a racetrack feel, packed with side paths, slopes, and shortcuts that were devoid of enemies/threats.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/MarchBlockoutFootage.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">Running around an early level blockout.</span> 
<p>
<b>While testing this version of the game, 3 key things were clear:</b>
<ul>
  <li> Players didn’t have an overview of how their defences were working 
  <li> The resource collection was so vastly different from the genre norms of Tower Defence games that players often just forgot to seek resource spawners out
  <li> It was a lot of fun to interact with enemies and players generally gravitated towards pushing them around and stomping on them
</ul>
</p>
<p>We are still making progress on the first point. UI and map updates are helping with player overview, but there is still more to be done. We decided to focus on bringing resource collection more in line with genre norms as that would impact points two and three.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/OreConcept.png" alt="Currency Collection Concept">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Concept art showing how currency was originally collected by the player.</span>

<h2 class="section-heading">Big feature changes</h2>
<p>We knew that the right way to reward the player with currency was by having them eliminate enemies. This is too much of a genre staple to mess around with (anymore). However, it was important that we still reward movement efficiency as well as give the player a reason to interact with enemies as much as possible (turning what’s fun into what must be done)!</p>
<p>We tried a few different ideas for this; gaining currency by clearing enemy corpses, gaining currency by last hitting enemies, etc. In the end we ended up with a new game object that would be placed around the level, the Shrine.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/ShrineAbsorb.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">Shrines absorb enemy souls.</span> 
<p>Any enemies killed within range of a Shrine will have its soul absorbed. The Shrine holds enemy souls like a piggy bank, and when the player needs to build more defences they must break the piggy bank to acquire the souls. A broken Shrine will no longer absorb enemy souls, so players are forced to build new nests of turrets further away from the Main Tower.</p>
<p>We are still figuring out how to properly tutorialise the feature, but players have reacted positively to the change so far. They are excited to engage with enemies as well as venture out further into the map to build at advantageous points. Min-maxing a Shrine’s soul collection, making strategic decisions about when to acquire the souls, and pushing/zoning enemies to keep them in range have all made the game more fun and replayable.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/ShrineCollect.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">Obtaining the collected souls means destroying the Shrine.</span> 
<p>On top of this, enemies killed outside the range of a Shrine spawn a soul that lingers on the map for a short amount of time. Players can grab these souls out of the air as they move around the level rewarding player movement efficiency with additional currency.</p>
<p>This was a bonus feature that ‘just made sense’ to add alongside the shrine functionality. It aligned perfectly with how we wanted players to engage with the game and understanding the idea of ‘lingering souls’ came quickly.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/LingeringSouls.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">Jumping to catch the 'lingering souls' of enemies killed outside Shrine range.</span> 

<h2 class="section-heading">Impacts to level design</h2>
<p>The introduction of Shrines has caused the levels we are designing to flatten out. Enemy paths weave and curve more so that players have an easier time taking advantage of Shrine range. Levels have more flat open space and a lot less gaps in the terrain to give players more building options with their turrets. Ultimately, the levels have started to look a lot more like a traditional Tower Defence when you look at the entire map from above (seems like a good direction).</p>
<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/PostShrineLevel.png" alt="WIP level post Shrines">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">An exmaple of a level designed after we implemented the Shrine feature.</span>
<p>We are still experimenting with level design procedures at the moment. It is important for us to understand what makes a level of <i>Tempest Tower</i> fun so that we can reliably produce great levels at a reasonable pace. There is probably another blog post in here about ‘character movement test level(s)’ and how they inform our design rules... But that's for another time.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/16/OctLevelFootage.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">Gathering Peepers in a level designed 'post-Shrines'.</span> 

<h2 class="section-heading">Stay up to date!</h2>
<p>The best way to stay informed about <i>Tempest Tower</i> is to wishlist the game on Steam and follow our community updates! Beyond that you can get more frequent updates by joining our <a href="http://hpy.lol/discord">Discord</a> or following us on Social Media (<a href="https://x.com/halfpastyellow">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/HalfPastYellow">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/halfpastyellow_/">Instagram</a>). You can also get less frequent updates by signing up for our <a href="https://newsletter.halfpastyellow.com/signup">newsletter</a>.</p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/3123800/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>]]></content><author><name>Max</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post was originally going to be about how we create an understandable player story within the whimsical/abstract world of Tempest Tower. Then I started to see the #blocktober tag around Twitter and decided to write a different post instead. Specifically, about some early experimentation we did on Tempest Tower and how changes to the game design impacted the level design. I don’t think that the hashtag has ever been as popular as 2017 when it was first started, but us indie developers must use every algorithm bump we can.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing: Tempest Tower</title><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/08/19/Introducing-Tempest-Tower.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing: Tempest Tower" /><published>2024-08-19T17:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-19T17:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/08/19/Introducing-Tempest-Tower</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/08/19/Introducing-Tempest-Tower.html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="section-heading">A New Project</h2>
<p>As hinted at in our <a href="/blog/2024/06/10/HPY-Update.html">last post</a>, we've been quite busy this year and are excited to announce our next project, <i>Tempest Tower</i>! It is an action-packed Tower Defence game with Platforming elements. We are bringing the much-loved character feel and animation style of <i>Time on Frog Island</i> to a new type of game. You will have to dodge and weave through waves of Creepers while maintaining your defences and herding the local critters to safety.</p>
<p>If that sounds like your kind of game, then I have good news for you! You can wishlist the game on Steam right now and get notified when the game launches.</p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/3123800/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>

<h2 class="section-heading">A Tower Defence with Platforming elements?</h2>
<p>The perfect mix of strategy and action. <i>Tempest Tower</i> offers traditional Tower Defense base building and wave-based gameplay with an added layer of player interaction. Push enemies around, personally activate traps, and jump on enemy heads while you save critters and collect resources.</p>
<p>Our goal for this project is to add a new level of tension to the Tower Defence genre by placing the player right in the middle of the action. You will have unlimited time to structure your defences and plan. When you activate the wave, you must trust your defences while you dodge, push, and stomp your way through hordes of enemies to collect resources and save cute little eyeball creatures called Peepers.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/15/PEEPR.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">These cute little guys can't defend themselves</span> 

<h2 class="section-heading">Push back the horde and claim victory</h2>
<p>My favorite mechanic is related to how we have structured the levels in <i>Tempest Tower</i>. At the start of a level, only a small portion of it will be available to explore. The rest of the level is covered in a thick fog. After successfully defending a wave, you will push back part of the fog and reveal a new section of the level.</p>
<p>Once you dispel the last of the fog, you will have one last wave of enemies to deal with before you claim victory on that map.</p>
<p>Pushing back the fog means pushing back enemy spawn points and gaining access to new strategic locations, but the Creepers will soon be back, and in greater numbers!</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/15/foglvl.png" alt="Fog Concept">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">A concept of the fog mechanic</span>

<p>This structure makes designing levels a really interesting challenge. We have spent a lot of time figuring out the right size of level, how much to reveal per wave, what tools the player needs to make traversal exciting, and so much more. Stay tuned for an in-depth level design blog later in the year 😉</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/15/blockout.png" alt="Fog Concept">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Colour coding is used to show level segments while blocking out the level design</span>

<h2 class="section-heading">HPY is going to Gamescom!</h2>
<p>Remy and I are in Cologne for Gamescom this week. We will be showcasing an early version of <i>Tempest Tower</i> at <a href="https://courage.events/event/courage-cologne-2024/">Courage Cologne 2024</a> on the 20th of August and we will be available at the event center during the rest of the week. If you manage to catch us at the showcase or on the show floor, you might be lucky enough to grab a <i>Tempest Tower</i> postcard.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/15/postcards.jpg" alt="Fog Concept">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Fancy limited edition postcards?!</span>

<h2 class="section-heading">Stay up to date</h2>
<p>Going forward we will be publishing a new blog post every 4-6 weeks, mostly about the development of <i>Tempest Tower</i>. You can get more frequent updates by joining our <a href="http://hpy.lol/discord">Discord</a> or following us on Social Media (<a href="https://x.com/halfpastyellow">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/HalfPastYellow">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/halfpastyellow_/">Instagram</a>). You can also get less frequent updates by signing up for our <a href="https://newsletter.halfpastyellow.com/signup">newsletter</a>.</p>
<p>See you next month!</p>]]></content><author><name>Max</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A New Project As hinted at in our last post, we've been quite busy this year and are excited to announce our next project, Tempest Tower! It is an action-packed Tower Defence game with Platforming elements. We are bringing the much-loved character feel and animation style of Time on Frog Island to a new type of game. You will have to dodge and weave through waves of Creepers while maintaining your defences and herding the local critters to safety. If that sounds like your kind of game, then I have good news for you! You can wishlist the game on Steam right now and get notified when the game launches.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spectacle is part of Steam Next Fest</title><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/06/10/Spectacle-Next-Fest.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spectacle is part of Steam Next Fest" /><published>2024-06-10T17:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-06-10T17:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/06/10/Spectacle-Next-Fest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/06/10/Spectacle-Next-Fest.html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="section-heading">Thank you for playing <i>Spectacle</i>!</h2>
<p>I want to thank everyone who took the time to check out the <i>Spectacle</i> Demo during the Cerebral Puzzle Fest. We received some great feedback via the Steam community hub and our Discord.</p>
<p>The <i>Spectacle</i> demo will be available again today as part of Steam Next Fest. After the event, we will keep the demo available forever. We are so excited to see <i>Spectacle</i> reach a wider audience.</p>

<p><i>Steam Next Fest</i> runs from <b>June 10th until June 17th</b> but the demo is forever!</p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/2996710/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>

<h2 class="section-heading">The world of Trip Space</h2>
<p>Eagle-eyed players will have seen small eyeball creatures (Peepers) running around. These creatures are visitors to Trip Space, excited to see all the strange sights. Peepers will be both a help and a hindrance during your journey.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/13/Concept.png" alt="concept image">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">A concept of the Peepers with Glo</span>

<p>We designed Peepers to inject charm into the game. <i>Spectacle</i> will only include a few lizard characters and we thought it was important that the game didn't feel too lonely to explore. We carefully crafted the colour, size, sounds, and animation to create the cutest little things we could.</p>
<p>Judging by tester feedback, I think we succeeded in our goal.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/13/PeeperRun.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">Don't spook the wildlife</span> 

<h2>Show us your speed</h2>
<p>If you’ve got what it takes to complete <i>Spectacle</i> in the blink of an eye, swing by <a href="https://discord.com/invite/8TkpjHHVzZ">our Discord Server</a> and post your completion time of the demo. The fastest time we have seen so far is 3 minutes and 44 seconds 😲</p>
<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/13/SpectacleDemoSpeed.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">Keep an eye out for your completion time</span>]]></content><author><name>Max</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thank you for playing Spectacle! I want to thank everyone who took the time to check out the Spectacle Demo during the Cerebral Puzzle Fest. We received some great feedback via the Steam community hub and our Discord. The Spectacle demo will be available again today as part of Steam Next Fest. After the event, we will keep the demo available forever. We are so excited to see Spectacle reach a wider audience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Half Past Yellow Update</title><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/06/10/HPY-Update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Half Past Yellow Update" /><published>2024-06-10T17:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-06-10T17:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/06/10/HPY-Update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/06/10/HPY-Update.html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="section-heading">Difficult times</h2>
<p>The game development industry has been having a hard time over the last year and a half. Studio closers, layoffs, and cancelled projects are a normal part of the news cycle now and it is difficult to tell when the bleeding will stop.</p>
<p>Half Past Yellow had to say goodbye to 2 of our team members in May due to uncertainty with project financing. The team members of HPY are the most valuable asset the studio has, and it feels terrible to lose key parts of it.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/14/team.jpg" alt="HPY team">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">The HPY team right after saving the world from a deadly virus</span>

<h2 class="section-heading">The struggle to secure funding</h2>
<p>Half Past Yellow started working on <i>Spectacle</i> in late 2022 and we have been showing off the game to potential publishers and investors as early as March 2023. It was already clear that the landscape for funding new projects was difficult to traverse, but we were optimistic that we would find a passionate publisher for the project by the end of the year. We persisted with the project, but as the year came to an end, it was clear that we weren’t getting the interest we hoped for. Most publishers cited similar concerns about the puzzle genre, specifically noting the ratio of ‘development cost’ to ‘playable hours’ as a difficult investment to justify in the current market.</p>
<p>In the beginning of 2024, we decided to start prototyping new games that had a stronger focus on action and replayability (a better ratio of ‘development cost’ and ‘playable hours’). We already had a commercially viable demo as well as a showcase build with more complicated puzzles, so it was possible to work on something new while seeking investment in Spectacle. In the past 6 months, we haven’t made any breakthroughs with Spectacle, but we have seen some early interest in our new project.</p>
<p>We believe that <i>Spectacle</i> requires an additional 12-18 months of development and this isn’t something that Half Past Yellow can commit to without the financial backing of a publisher or investment partner. Because of this, we have made the difficult decision to fully switch projects.</p>

<h2 class="section-heading">What is happening with Spectacle?</h2>
<p>We were so excited to release the <i>Spectacle</i> demo and we are ecstatic that players enjoyed the game. The demo was released to show off the game that we have been diligently working on over the course of 2023 as well as give us some concrete information about player interest in a full game.</p>
<p>It was impossible for us to back up the demo launch with a proper marketing push, so we had to rely on word of mouth and Steam’s algorithm to be noticed. <i>Spectacle</i> saw good traction in the smaller Cerebral Puzzle Showcase but failed to get any real interest during Next Fest.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/14/wishlists.png" alt="HPY team">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">We saw a good bump in wishlists during puzzle fest, but not enough to change our fate</span>

<p>The <i>Spectacle</i> demo will remain available on Steam forever and we are excited by the prospect of returning to the project one day, but the internal status is currently: delayed indefinitely.</p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/2996710/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>


<h2 class="section-heading">What does the future hold?</h2>
<p>The team is ready to show off the project that we started prototyping at the beginning of this year. We will be sharing gameplay footage on our <a href="http://hpy.lol/discord">Discord</a>, <a href="https://x.com/halfpastyellow">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/HalfPastYellow">Facebook</a>, and <a href="https://www.instagram.com/halfpastyellow_/">Instagram</a> over the next 4-6 weeks as we build up to a proper announcement and Steam page launch. I hope you take the time to check it out and let us know what you think. In the meantime, a sneak peak will have to do.</p>

<div class="text-center">
<video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/14/NewfirstPost_smol.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">Top down platforming action with a twist...</span>]]></content><author><name>Max</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Difficult times The game development industry has been having a hard time over the last year and a half. Studio closers, layoffs, and cancelled projects are a normal part of the news cycle now and it is difficult to tell when the bleeding will stop. Half Past Yellow had to say goodbye to 2 of our team members in May due to uncertainty with project financing. The team members of HPY are the most valuable asset the studio has, and it feels terrible to lose key parts of it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Play the Spectacle Demo!</title><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/05/23/Spectacle-Demo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Play the Spectacle Demo!" /><published>2024-05-23T17:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-23T17:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/05/23/Spectacle-Demo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2024/05/23/Spectacle-Demo.html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="section-heading">It's been... a while...</h2>
<p>
Wow, it has been a year and a half since our last blog post. Our biggest gap yet 🛹 </p>
<p>A lot has happened in that time, and we are excited to update you with this blog post and one coming next month. </p>

<h2 class="section-heading">Witness a <i>Spectacle</i>!</h2>
<p>
Last year we announced our next game, <i>Spectacle</i>. A surreal first-person puzzle game about observation, spatial reasoning, and lizards. The core mechanics of <i>Spectacle</i> revolve around blinking, winking, and wearing special glasses that transform how you interact with the world. 
</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet tw-align-center"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Enter the surreal and mind-bending world of <i>Spectacle</i> – a new first-person puzzle game 👁<br>We can finally reveal the game we’ve been working on and look forward to hearing what you think! Check out the game and wishlist below 👇🦎<a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/WishlistWednesday?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#WishlistWednesday</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/gamedev?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#gamedev</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/indiegame?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#indiegame</a> <a href="https://t.co/nWmoqEzqlm">pic.twitter.com/nWmoqEzqlm</a></p>&mdash; 🟡 Half Past Yellow (@halfpastyellow) <a href="https://twitter.com/halfpastyellow/status/1734870273617547470?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 13, 2023</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<h2 class="section-heading">Play Today!</h2>
<p>
We are happy to announce that you can play a demo version of <i>Spectacle</i> TODAY! We have been selected to show <i>Spectacle</i> alongside many other great puzzle games during the <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/sale/CerebralPuzzleShowcase">Cerebral Puzzle Showcase</a> presented by <a href="https://www.draknek.org/">Draknek & Friends</a>. </p>

<p>
The event runs from <b> May 23rd until May 30th</b>, don't miss it!
</p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/2996710/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>

<p>
You get to play the tutorial sequence, and at the end, you will get a sneak peek of the ‘first proper level’ of the full game. Take control of Glo, a newly hatched lizard who learns about the world of Trip Space while you explore the surreal world of <i>Spectacle</i> and engage with its puzzles. 
</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" style="max-width:60%" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/12/Glo.png" alt="Demo Image">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">An early concept of the main character, Glo.</span> 


<h2 class="section-heading">A new way to perceive puzzles</h2>

<p>
<i>Spectacle</i> offers a novel puzzle solving experience with unique mechanics and controls. The game began life as an exploration of tele-rotating the player in 3D space with a “match cut” and continued to grow from there.  
</P>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/12/TeleRotate.gif" alt="Demo Image">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Same, same...</span> 

<p>
A lot has changed since then and I’m so happy to finally be sharing Spectacle publicly. I hope that players have as much fun playing it as we did making it. 
</P>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/12/AbstractSpaces.gif" alt="Demo Image">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">... but different!</span> 



<h2 class="section-heading">Tell us what you think!</h2>

<p>
The HPY Discord is slowly growing. If you aren’t already a member of our little community, we would love to have you join and share your experiences with the <i>Spectacle</i> Demo. We are gearing up to announce something new soon and <a href="https://discord.com/invite/8TkpjHHVzZ">our Discord Server</a> is the best way to stay up to date. </P>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/2996710/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>]]></content><author><name>Max</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It's been... a while... Wow, it has been a year and a half since our last blog post. Our biggest gap yet 🛹 A lot has happened in that time, and we are excited to update you with this blog post and one coming next month.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy Holidays 2023!</title><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2022/12/22/Happy-Holidays-2023.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy Holidays 2023!" /><published>2022-12-22T16:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-22T16:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2022/12/22/Happy-Holidays-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2022/12/22/Happy-Holidays-2023.html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="section-heading">Thank you for playing Time on Frog Island!</h2>

<p>
Games take a monumental amount of time and effort to develop, and releasing is a scary moment for any studio. The community response to the game is everything we hoped for and more, seeing players enjoy their time on Frog Island has been so rewarding for us, and hearing fun stories from friends and fans never gets old. We hope this is just the first of many Half Past Yellow adventures that fans enjoy. 
</p>

<div class="text-center">
  <video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/10/GameplayTrailer_v02.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 

<p>
For those of you who haven’t picked up the game yet, Time on Frog Island is part the winter sale on all platforms so there has never been a better time to buy! 
</p>

<p>
<i>Time on Frog Island</i> is on sale digitally on:<br>
<ul>
<li> <u><a href="https://www.xbox.com/en-US/games/store/time-on-frog-island/9pmvswxvp8m5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Xbox</a></u> until January 3rd
  <li> <u><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1717510/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Steam</a></u> until January 5th
  <li> <u><a href="https://store.epicgames.com/en-US/p/trading-time-b3ad0d" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Epic Game Store</a></u> until January 5th
  <li> <u><a href="https://www.nintendo.com/store/products/time-on-frog-island-switch/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Switch</a></u> until January 10th  
  <li> <u><a href="https://store.playstation.com/en-us/concept/10003789/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">PlayStation</a></u> until January 18th
</ul>
</p>

<h2 class="section-heading">To the moon!</h2>

<p>
<i>Time on Frog Island</i> has also just launched on Amazon Luna as part of the Luna+ subscription bundle. This is the 8th platform that <i>Time on Frog Island</i> has been released on, and we are so excited to see what Luna users think of the game! 
</P>

<div class="text-center">
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/luna/detail/B0BQ8DTM9Y" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/11/ToTheMoon.jpg" alt="Demo Image"></a>
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Tell your friends!</span> 

<h2 class="section-heading">Patched up and ready to go</h2>

<p>
As of mid-November, our first bug-fixing patch for <i>Time on Frog Island</i> was released across all platforms. It took a while to make it onto consoles due to some logistical issues on our side, but everything is up and running now with everyone on the same version of the game. 
</P>

<p>
The patch fixes a few niggling bugs seen around the island, plus some bigger bugs associated with The Merchant and The Blacksmith schedules not being properly updated. We have also fixed a bug blocking some players from getting the Frogs Legs, Sea Legs, and Yeet trophies/achievements (sorry about that trophy hunters). 
</P>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/11/PatchedUp.jpg" alt="Demo Image">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">About time!</span>

<h2 class="section-heading">Time on Frog Island OST now available!</h2>
<p>
It is now possible to take our cosy island vibes with you wherever you go! The <i>Time on Frog Island</i> soundtrack is now available for purchase on Steam. We don’t have a timeline yet, but we would like to bring the OST to other platforms (such as Spotify) as well. Let us know which ones you use! We will keep you posted on that progress. </p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/1927320/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>

<h2 class="section-heading">What is next for Half Past Yellow?</h2>

<p>
At Half Past Yellow, we are consistently curious about different genres and technology. We will always bring the same HPY charm and style to all of our games, but each project will be different to the one that came before. We are really excited for 2023, production has already begun on our next project and we can’t wait until we get to show it off. Until then you will just have to keep your eyes peeled! 👁️
</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/11/HPYHols.png" alt="A polaroid of Time on Frog Island characters">
</div>

<h2 class="section-heading">See you on the other side!</h2>

<p>
That's it for now! From all of us here at HPY, we hope you have a relaxing holiday and a great year ahead of you!
</p>

<div class="text-center">
  <video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/5/Tree_Light.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Max</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thank you for playing Time on Frog Island!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Time on Frog Island - Out Now!</title><link href="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2022/07/12/ToFI-Launch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Time on Frog Island - Out Now!" /><published>2022-07-12T17:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-07-12T17:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2022/07/12/ToFI-Launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/2022/07/12/ToFI-Launch.html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="section-heading">Let's gooo!</h2>

<p>
Half Past Yellow is finally proud to present <i>Time on Frog Island</i>! To celebrate, here's a catchy sing-along frog song:
</p>

<div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 rounded">
	<iframe class="embed-responsive-item" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/K06BAU1WfSY" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>

<p>
After two-and-a-half years in development we're so excited to hear what everyone thinks! We can't wait to see what kind of shenanigans everyone gets up to! </P>

<p>As always, the best place to connect with us and other fans is <a href="https://discord.com/invite/8TkpjHHVzZ">our Discord!</a></P>

<div class="text-center">
  <video class="video-fluid bordered" autoplay loop controls muted src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/10/GameplayTrailer_v02.mp4" type ="video/mp4"></>
</div> 
<span class="caption text-muted">Hop, skip, jump!</span> 

<h2 class="section-heading">Out where?!</h2>
<p>
Time on Frog island is available at (at least!) all these clicks right here:<br>
<b>Digital!</b>
<ul>
  <li> <u><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1717510/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Steam</a></u>
  <li> <u><a href="https://store.epicgames.com/en-US/p/trading-time-b3ad0d" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Epic Game Store</a></u>
  <li> <u><a href="https://store.playstation.com/en-us/concept/10003789/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">PlayStation</a></u>
  <li> <u><a href="https://www.xbox.com/en-US/games/store/time-on-frog-island/9pmvswxvp8m5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Xbox</a></u>
  <li> <u><a href="https://www.nintendo.com/store/products/time-on-frog-island-switch/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Switch</a></u>
  <li> <u><a href="https://stadia.google.com/game/time-on-frog-island" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stadia</a></u>
</ul>
<b>Physical!</b>
<ul>
  <li> <u><a href="https://signatureeditiongames.com/search?type=product&options%5Bprefix%5D=last&q=time+on+frog+island" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Signature Edition Games</a></u>
  <li> Your local game store?!
</ul>
</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/9/ToFIRetail.jpg" alt="Demo Image">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">So many flavours!</span>

<h2 class="section-heading">Not yet conviced? Try the Prologue!</h2>
<p>
In case you've made it here and are not yet convinced - we do have a <b>free</b> prologue for you to check out on Steam.
</p>

<div class="text-center"><iframe src="https://store.steampowered.com/widget/1755950/" frameborder="0" width="646" height="190"></iframe></div>

<h2 class="section-heading">The journey begins!</h2>

<p>
Thanks for following us on this chapter of our journey!</P>

<p>
From everyone here at Half Past Yellow, we're very pleased to share our creation with you and we sincerely hope you enjoy your <i>Time on Frog Island</i>! 💛
</p>

<div class="text-center">
<img class="img-fluid bordered" src="https://halfpastyellow.com/blog/img/posts/10/PolaroidLong.png" alt="A polaroid of Time on Frog Island characters">
</div>
<span class="caption text-muted">Wish you were here!</span>]]></content><author><name>Remy</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let's gooo!]]></summary></entry></feed>